[Music]
hi it's Jennifer from shabby fabrics I
have an amazing project for you today
it's the jelly roll rug I have never had
so much fun being involved in a project
as making this jelly roll rug we get
these pre-cut sin and of course my boys
thinking about quilts and I'm thinking
about table runners but RJ designs came
up with a jelly roll rug pattern and
Roma
bless her heart has given us permission
to show you certain parts of how the rug
goes together now the pattern is
excellent she has wonderful instructions
so be sure to get your pattern and this
is one jelly roll makes this rug and it
was as I said an absolute blast I'm
completely addicted and now I can't wait
to make them out of this joy bowl and
that jelly roll so they make amazing
gifts and these rugs are firm you can
walk on them you can throw them in the
washing machine the dryer and they will
last and they will last and they will
last so this is so much fun now products
have come out that make this process
even easier Roman lets you know that you
can cut either batting strips and you
would be actually taping those strips
together
well she uses a batting seam tape or
bosal has come out with this katadyn on
a roll it's basically the softest most
organic lovely wonderful strips that are
already cut for either two and a half
inches and this is 50 yards long it'll
take two of these to do one of the rugs
and your favorite jelly roll and of
course you'll be getting this pattern
now what we've decided to do to offer
this as a can't for you as you're
putting together two of the Cadogan
rolls you'll be getting Roma's jelly
roll rug that a jelly roll rug pattern
this is a kit and then you'll simply
pick your favorite jelly roll
we'll also be selling the katadyn
separately so when you want to make
additional rugs since you don't need to
buy the pattern more than once you'll be
able to just get more of the two and a
half inch strips and get your favorite
jelly rolls so we're making all that
available and I love that bosal came out
with that and
it's the softest most wonderful thing
and you know yes you could cut your own
batting strips but then you're having to
tape them together with that seam tape
and this just makes it more available to
jump into the projects and jump right
into the sewing which of course I love
that part so let's get started
as I said it takes one jelly roll now oh
and by the way this is Emma's garden
from a wood studio I love that
collection we have all kinds of pre-cut
kits and beautiful kits we've designed
here with that collection so the rug
coordinates beautifully with that of
course pre-cuts have a limited life so a
lot of manufacturers will do them just
one time as the collection is coming out
so if you do find the Jelly Roll you
love absolutely grab it absolutely grab
one or maybe even two because I know
with motive for example they typically
have pre-cut one time at the beginning
of a collection and not again with that
collection so they do have limited
availability and again grab those
because you're going to find so many
projects to do with them the one I'll be
working on today and if you can see on
the overhead camera is detour ahead this
is from Wilmington now it's one of the
things that Wilmington does is they
offer their two and a half inch strip in
two different quantities this is the 24
pack and they also offer a larger pack
we're carrying the 24 pack so in this
instance you would need two of these to
do one rug and then actually make the
rug just a little bit bigger because
you'll be getting 48 strips versus most
jelly rolls have about 42 42 once you
get ready to decide you've decided what
collection you want to use you've got
your pre-cut in front of you obviously
you know let me just let me just say
this as an aside let's say that let's
say you fall in love with a collection
but you can't get more of those jelly
roll strips you know that you could
always cut your own 20 half inch strips
and make your own jelly roll so don't
worry if if your favorite collection you
can't find those jelly rolls anymore you
just make your own so I opened up my
package and I'm lit first thing I'm
going to do is decide in this instance
we said you know we really want to have
the green on the interior have some
white and come back with our dark purple
on the outside that's completely your
preference how you want to lay your
strips out and as you can see that's
going to determine how your rug is going
to look in the end so step one is when
you get your once you decide you have
your strips ready make sure you have
about 40 strips right in there maybe a
little bit more a little bit less
obviously a little bit less is just
gonna have a smaller rug a little bit
more I can have a bigger rug lay them
out in the order in which you want them
to appear so I'm gonna bring this over a
little bit more centered this is going
to be the center of my rug and my blue
is going to be the outside of my rug as
you would expect we need to just get
those arranged then I'm gonna stack
these here just put these here and that
I need to sew my strips together and you
know when I'm piecing a quilt block
I am very precise of how I splice things
together especially if I'm doing like a
half square triangles and here we just
went for it
this is a rug it's not a precise quilt
block so let me put that off there then
come to the sewing machine so this is my
first strip so let's just put that
that's a little bit slippery there let's
put that like that now my next strip I
notice I haven't even taken off myself
at yet I'm just gonna lay that 90
degrees to that I have a normal straight
stitch as you would expect my stitch
length right now is a 2.0 and I'm just
gonna turn now I have learned
that when I look where I want to end up
it's where I end up it seems to be very
consistent that when I just look here
this is where I end up sewing
all right now this is the one I just so
it's on the lay that like this and I'm
gonna grab my next strip which happens
to be the same fabric and this
particular pack from detour ahead by
Wilmington there are some duplicates and
that's fine you can either do that next
trip or you could put it somewhere else
that arrangement of the rug is one of
the fun things I think too about the
project as depending on how you arrange
this it's going to of course look
different let me get that out of the way
real quick there we go don't want to
show that twice so again I'm gonna look
right here
and that's where I'm going to end up
okay let's do one more this is my strip
lay that down and I'm just going to
change this up just for fun I want to
get a different fabric let's do this one
okay you get the idea now you will do
this for all of your strips all forty or
however number strips you have you're
going to do this all the way down this
ensures it's going to be in the order
that you want
all right now we are going to just do
three strips you get the idea you would
just keep going keep going you're gonna
have a long that's a lot of strips sewn
together it's a lot of length put those
down there real quick so the first thing
I'm going to do before I do any kind of
pressing is I'm just going to go ahead
and clip this clip them apart and bring
them to my mat I'm just going to cut
those apart
I'll use my quarter inch let's use this
quarter inch here now you can bring this
right to your pressing your pressing is
next you can either just bring this to
your ironing board or work on this table
initially and we're just going to repeat
that so you're just gonna cut those
apart because of course you stink chain
stitch to everything grab your four and
a half by I love this ruler you know I
mean I've got of course I have different
size rulers but I don't need a bigger
ruler than this it's already taking up a
lot of space so having a ruler that
really fits the job and the size that
you need is just so ideal so if you
don't have any smaller rulers this is a
great one to have I feel like I grab
that ruler so much because I do have
limited space I have a lot of things on
the table all the time and I don't want
my big ruler that I use to cut you know
big width of fabric strips alright so
you would go to obviously we would have
pitched everything together I'm going to
go cut everything apart in that same
fashion now we're going to let's get our
iron going now this is a step we we've
made the rug twice something Tammy
discovered when she made this and she
did an incredible job didn't she good
job Tammy I mean she's incredible he has
no she didn't use sizing on that and on
this one she's using sizing and finding
that it's coming out so a beautifully
flat which of course you want that so we
really recommend the sizing that's
neither but I believe that's not in the
pattern it's just something that Tammy
discovered and so I'm gonna pass that
tip on to you as well
whenever Tammy has a tip boy I'm
listening because she knows she finds
very clever ways to do things and more
efficient ways to do things and
sometimes uses extra products like
sizing to make something come out even
better than otherwise it would have
otherwise so we went ahead and we're
gonna size everything better iron all
going here seems because we want this to
lay as flat as possible as you might
expect we want you to go ahead and press
the seams open I know Roma mentions that
in the pattern as well to press the
seams open so for that reason my stitch
length is 2.5 or shorter don't go longer
than that because you are opening up
that seam so here we're coming up to a
seam right now and then I'm going to
show you how she recommends to kind of
manage this big long piece of now joined
strips into a a very long piece of of
fabric when you have you know 40 strips
that are each 40-plus inches that's a
lot of length so what she has you do she
kind of has your fan fold it so you have
put that here and kind of fold it back
on to itself as you work so it's a way
to manage this so again you would keep
sizing that you saw that press the seam
open and let me just show you the fan
fold kind of put your finger there and
you kind of go back and forth and you go
back and forth and so it's a way to just
kind of manage the fabric
because you have so much of it and
you'll just go back and forth back and
forth pressing your seams open adding
your sizing etc etc so you have this
whole thing in this nice stack then
typically when you move to the move to
the sewing machine you're going to have
this either on your lap on the ground
it's it's just a lot to manage it's what
I'll be doing is moving the table next
to me but before we even jump into that
step the next thing we're going to be
doing as we'll be using I'm gonna use
this one just to show it to you now
she'll get you started Roma's got great
starting instructions of how you kind of
get your strip started but I want to
show you how to manage the katadyn which
is your batting strip with this and the
wonder clips we found the wonder clips
to be literally wonderful they are so
fantastic I love how this is pre-cut and
fits perfectly on the back of my
two-and-a-half inch strip it's the
precision of that is probably something
in me that I like very much so as you
can see
you're obviously putting that batting
strip on the back of your fabric fold
toward the middle fold toward the middle
let me see if I can line that it up even
better fold to the middle and now you'll
just sandwich that and making sure that
that is stack stack exactly on top of
each other okay now you would start this
project actually a little bit
differently but I'm just showing you how
to get the batting on the back of the
fabric and how you keep the layers
together before you move them to the
sewing machine let me show you what I've
actually started already with this and
it might be easier for you to see it
this way I've started wonder clipping it
the other things she has you do as you
start sewing this together it's this
thing it's like this big long thing she
has you start rolling up I told her my
cat my cat would love this thing
um you start kind of rolling this up so
it's manageable so you can see how I've
wanted to clip that let's let's do this
again it's back here tucked in tucked in
make sure when you fold this that top
portion is stacked exactly on top of the
bottom portion and we recommend Wondra
clipping and not pinning as you can
imagine this is a lot of pins if it was
pins and you're gonna be poking yourself
those pins maybe coming out
I love the security of the Wonder clips
they're easy to take out no one's
getting poked and they're fun I love the
colorful ones and they're just wonderful
to use they're a wonderful alternative
to using pins alright so as you can see
you're going to clip as far down as you
can so you want run out of wonder clips
then you'll take it to the sewing
machine you're going to be using a
standard quarter inch seam allowance you
may want to reduce the pressure on the
presser foot itself if your machine can
do that this is a lot of bulk moving
under the machine now the Bernina has
the capability of reducing the pressure
on the presser foot itself but if your
machine doesn't no worries at all but
you might want to look about that if
it's possible to do that on your machine
now at home if I was throwing this
sitting down which of course I would be
I would be putting this strip set on the
ground and the cattigan on the ground in
this case because I'm standing I'm just
gonna move it the table next to me and
what I think we can manage it this way
so let's move that over here as you can
imagine this takes up a lot of space so
make sure wherever you're working maybe
a dining room table you have lots of
space and have the table cleaned off
because as you move this project around
you start it's going to clean off your
table if you haven't already so let's
put this on here let's bring that to our
get my table closer
what table works pretty cool we were
doing this in the sewing room sitting
down I haven't done this standing up and
it's actually very manageable to have it
on a table next to me I'm gonna put my
wonder Clips right here so as I'm taking
them off I can just put them in there
and now I'm standing sewing a standard
quarter inch seam allowance I just
picked a thread that I thought might
look best with all of the different
fabrics let me back check that just a
little bit and I'm making sure that that
top roll is on top of the bottom roll if
you find it scoots out stop and rip it
out and go back don't keep going you
don't want this rug to fall apart over
time because it's going to be walked on
it's going to be used it's going to be
washed it's going to be dried so you'll
just keep going of course this Bernina
handles it beautifully
and you'll just keep going so I'm just
gonna cut my stitch right and cut my
thread right now because I want to show
you the next step here it's no mystery
I'm going to sew until I run out of
wonder clips and then i'ma stop I'm
gonna fold more of the batting to the
back of the fabric 1 2 clip and so again
until I'm all the way at the end roll
this up and make my nice big ball oK
we've already done all that now I want
to show you I'll need a switch press
repeat real quick because now you'll be
using a zig zag stitch and I believe
Roma suggests a 5.5 in width I believe
and it's in here I believe it's at 5.5
and it might be a 2.2 what I love how
she gets that specific where she tells
you even things to that to that degree
I know it's program in here so let me
look up let me look at the actual
setting on that now I'm gonna go ahead
and release this is my dual feed on my
Bernina I'm gonna change this presser
foot real quick I love the quick release
on the Bernina it makes changing presser
feet just a snap and this Brina 770
actually knows what presser foot is on
here which I love that too ok so it's a
5.5 in width the length is 2.0 we've
already started our rug I better move
this over here because we're gonna need
some more space so I can show you how
this works
I'm just do a little bit of rearranging
here and you'll be doing the same thing
you just need to make space just bring
our machine over and more ok
so shear at Roma recommends once you
have your ball you might want to put
that in a basket so I brought a basket
with me today
I don't just kind of put that in there
okay so I'm gonna take this off so that
I can it'll it'll release as it needs to
this step here we've already started our
rug and it's going so I just want to
show you how I'm gonna put this actually
down with me because I need it to be in
front of me you don't need to pin here
you don't need to wonder clip here
you're just going to start sewing and
lay this now don't tug on this because
if you pull on these strips when you
kind of relax them your rug is gonna
maybe have a little bit of a ripple or
an accordion fact you're just laying
that next to it with no pressure and
letting the machine do the work for you
so let's start sewing I'm definitely
gonna back tack
and I'm just laying that next to it so
I'm not pushing I'm not pulling I'm just
letting the machine use that zigzag to
draw those layers together and secure
them
look at that look at that how fun is
that and then you will simply continue
all the way around and again Roma's
awesome instructions tell you how to
finish your rug so if you've never done
something like this I hadn't before and
it's absolutely a blast so I encourage
you to grab your favorite jelly rolls
grabbed at Canada and grab this amazing
pattern these make wonderful gifts and
they're wonderful for your own home so
thank you for letting me share the jelly
roll rug pattern with you today
[Music]